<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ponds | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://royrusso.github.io/blog/categories/ponds/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://royrusso.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T14:08:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://royrusso.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Build a Pond]]></title>
    <link href="http://royrusso.github.io/blog/2009/09/18/i-build-a-pond/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-18T04:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://royrusso.github.io/blog/2009/09/18/i-build-a-pond</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Those that know me personally, know my love for fish. It is likely amplified by the fact that I was born and raised in Miami, yet now find myself land-locked in Atlanta with the nearest ocean a 5-hour drive away. I have several fresh-water aquariums (Asian 30g planted tank pictured here)  in-house,  but this late-summer I decided to take my love for fish outdoors, by building a pond (in a rather muddy and useless part of my backyard).</p>

<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOPCA3gI4I/AAAAAAAAAAM/xb6e3_F9O94/s1600-h/DSC03739.JPG"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOPCA3gI4I/AAAAAAAAAAM/xb6e3_F9O94/s320/DSC03739.JPG" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The goal was to build a pond on a strict budget (I&rsquo;m cheap!), thus requiring me to build most of it by hand, using the least amount of store-bought parts as possible. So I started digging&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip; and I didn&rsquo;t stop until the hole was 3ft at its deepest point, with several shelves sculpted along the edges at varying depths. Georgia clay is not Miami sand. Digging this 1500gallon hole took me 2 full weekends or 4 days of non-stop pick and shovel work, but once it was complete, it was time to place the under-liner. I found some Uhaul padding cloths that would work nicely, from the garage&hellip;</p>

<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrORqCJUl3I/AAAAAAAAAAc/KHOiBfkQpW8/s1600-h/DSC03675.JPG"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrORqCJUl3I/AAAAAAAAAAc/KHOiBfkQpW8/s320/DSC03675.JPG" alt="" /></a>
I didn&rsquo;t skimp on the liner itself and bought 45epdm liner at the <a href="http://www.atlantawatergardens.com/">Atlanta Water Garden store</a> ($270!) along with a 1800g/hr submersible pump ($150). I looked at the liners available at Lowes/HDepot, and didn&rsquo;t want the low quality/price, because one hole in a liner would be a mess to fix. Once the liner was in place, the real work/engineering started on the filter. I wasn&rsquo;t going to spend a minimum of $300 an a filter and another $300 on a skimmer, so I went the homemade bio-filter route. Using the <a href="http://www.skippysstuff.com/minime.htm">Skippy site</a> and this <a href="http://leisure.prior-it.co.uk/build-diy-pond-bio-filter.shtml">crazy british guy&rsquo;s site</a> as a guide, I built my own filter using a plain-old rubbermaid tank, pvc tubing, pvc valves, lava rock, and scotch-brite-like scrubbie pads (Dollar-store &ndash; $10). The lava-rock and scrubbies are used as a &ldquo;house&rdquo; for all that beneficial bacteria that will live there and eat-up all the junk that algae likes to feed on.</p>

<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOYeuIacbI/AAAAAAAAAA0/Mg8l-hT6uPg/s1600-h/Picture+014.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOYeuIacbI/AAAAAAAAAA0/Mg8l-hT6uPg/s320/Picture+014.jpg" alt="" /></a>
I also added several plants, like Anachris, Water Lettuce, two-leaf and four-leaf water clover. The plants will also compete with the algae and provide oxygen to the fish, so they&rsquo;re not gasping for air. Within a few months, I should have crystal-clear water. Total cost for the filter was $50. Plants ran about $20.</p>

<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOUhaAwlwI/AAAAAAAAAAk/FHkbCWNtPTA/s1600-h/Picture+012.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOUhaAwlwI/AAAAAAAAAAk/FHkbCWNtPTA/s320/Picture+012.jpg" alt="" /></a>Once the pond was filled, I bought some cheap-o fish&hellip; 20 minnows and 20 goldfish &ndash; total cost $7. Most people use these as feeders, and I wasn&rsquo;t about to spend $200 on a koi!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve done some work on the tubing since I filled the pond, painting all visible parts black with spray paint and burying most of the water-routing. I also got a great deal on stone-work for the edging from Lowes.</p>

<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOVt_h4xkI/AAAAAAAAAAs/Fkqvv6MlwxQ/s1600-h/DSC03735.JPG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_o-_Iw9XoQXU/SrOVt_h4xkI/AAAAAAAAAAs/Fkqvv6MlwxQ/s320/DSC03735.JPG" alt="" /></a>
Although the original design called for the shape to be of a kidney-bean, somehow when I started digging it turned in to an oval. ;&ndash;) Luckily the shape works well with the location of the waterfall and pump, helping circulate water around the planted plants, so there aren&rsquo;t any dead spots for algae to take hold and junk to collect.</p>

<p>Things left to do&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Landscaping the area around the pond and create a viewing/sitting area.</p></li>
<li><p>Purchase a palette of slate for the waterfall. It is currently using rocks I found during the Big Dig.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>As expected, there was an algae bloom within a week of the pond being filled. It&rsquo;s starting to subside now as the bacteria and plants take hold. I&rsquo;ll post pictures next month and hopefully, I&rsquo;m not staring at pea-soup. ;&ndash;)</p>

<p>The only design flaw thus far, I didn&rsquo;t account for, was water overflow. It&rsquo;s been raining a lot here lately, forcing me to open the drainage valve under the filter manually to drain the pond. If the water breaches the walls (think New Orleans levies), things can get ugly really fast, so building some automated overflow in the system will likely be a winter task.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
